<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "journalpub-cals3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" article-type="top">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">invivo</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>IN VIVO</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0733-1398</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Informa, Inc.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2015800056</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">2015800056</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Category">
          <subject>Feature Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Geography">
          <subject></subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Industries">
          <subject>Biopharmaceuticals</subject>
          <subject>Vaccines</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Subjects">
          <subject>Deals Dealmaking Strategies</subject>
          <subject>Business Strategies</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Therapeutic Categories">
          <subject></subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Market Segments">
          <subject></subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Global Vaccines: A Shot Of Growth For GSK And Pfizer?</article-title>
        <subtitle></subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>04</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>33</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright 2015 Informa Business Information, Inc., an Informa Company. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
        <p>Recent M&amp;A activity in the vaccine industry has narrowed the pool of players. For companies that remain, the opportunity to reshape their positions in the global market comes with an even greater responsibility to contribute meaningfully to continued advances in global public health.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="long">
        <p>The $25 billion global vaccine industry, dominated by just a handful of major companies, is in flux. The past 15 months have seen a flurry of M&amp;A activity and the exit of two players. This consolidation concentrates the responsibility for vaccine discovery, development, and manufacturing in the hands of a few firms that have the resources to have a global impact on disease prevention and a commitment to vaccines as a strategic aspect of their overall business. With the departure of two of the top five vaccine manufacturers, these companies now carry an even greater burden of providing for the prevention needs of the global community. Deals by GSK and Pfizer, two of the remaining players, highlight the particular opportunity for meningococcal B vaccines. Success in developed markets will provide an important impetus for implementation of guidelines and product adoption elsewhere in the world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="deck" />
      <counts>
        <word-count count="4158" />
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>publish_datetime</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2015-04-14 08:00:00.000</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>lastupdated_datetime</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2015-06-24 18:19:33.012</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>end_datetime</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2999-12-31 00:00:00.000</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>created_datetime</meta-name>
          <meta-value>0001-01-01 00:00:00.000</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>modified_datetime</meta-name>
          <meta-value>0001-01-01 00:00:00.000</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>story_datetime</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2015-04-14 08:00:00.000</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue_date</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2015-04-23 00:00:00.000</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>article_size</meta-name>
          <meta-value />
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>content_type</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Article</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <list list-type="bullet" id="L0">
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">The $25 billion global vaccine industry, dominated by just a handful of major companies, is in flux. The past 15 months have seen a flurry of M&amp;A activity and the exit of two players.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">This consolidation concentrates the responsibility for vaccine discovery, development, and manufacturing in the hands of a few firms that have the resources to have a global impact on disease prevention and a commitment to vaccines as a strategic aspect of their overall business.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">With the departure of two of the top five vaccine manufacturers, these companies now carry an even greater burden of providing for the prevention needs of the global community.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">Deals by GSK and Pfizer, two of the remaining players, highlight the particular opportunity for meningococcal B vaccines. Success in developed markets will provide an important impetus for implementation of guidelines and product adoption elsewhere in the world.</p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">The modern era of preventative vaccines began over 200 years ago with Edward Jenner&#8217;s pioneering work on a vaccine to prevent smallpox.  As science advanced, additional vaccines were developed to prevent a broad range of deadly or debilitating diseases, including cholera, rabies, tetanus, influenza, polio, and, in more recent years, meningitis, human papillomavirus, and rotavirus.  This scientific work, coupled with progress in the delivery of vaccines to populations in need throughout the world, has resulted in millions of lives saved, virtually eliminating a number of diseases. Vaccines have been identified as one of the greatest public health achievements of all time.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">In 2015, the global vaccine industry will have revenue of approximately $25 billion, most of which is attributable to a few major multinational companies.  The industry is currently experiencing a period of significant change as major players attempt to strengthen their market position through acquisition of products and technologies while marginal players exit the business.  This phase of industry evolution will further concentrate the responsibility for vaccine discovery, development, and manufacturing in the hands of a few firms with enough resources to have a global impact on disease prevention and a renewed commitment to vaccines as a strategic aspect of their overall business.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      There is a considerable opportunity for these investments to be rewarded:  over the next five years, the industry is poised for average annual growth of over 10% based on promising new products and a strengthened commitment to immunization by public health authorities throughout the world.  Although the industry will remain concentrated during this dynamic period, there are still opportunities for changes in market position between competitors.  To secure a strong market position and justify significant outlays, the major competitors will need to act on opportunities that are specific to their situation and represent challenges to their execution skills. Recent moves by <bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/198601356" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>GlaxoSmithKline PLC</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold> and  <bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/198600199" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>Pfizer Inc.</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold>, two companies at the forefront of industry dealmaking activity, have disrupted the vaccine industry and have highlighted the particular opportunity for meningococcal B vaccines in developed countries.
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Sub-head">Consolidation And Exits Mark 2014</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      By comparison to the global pharmaceutical market at over $750 billion per year in revenue, the vaccines industry is relatively small; however, in percentage terms total revenue has grown significantly over the last 15 years from $5 billion in 2000 to an estimated $25 billion in 2014. (<italic>See Exhibit 1.</italic>) This rapid growth has created an attractive opportunity for pharmaceutical firms striving to offset patent expiries and market challenges to their drug business.  Due to high entry barriers, however, this growth has not attracted new large-company entrants to the vaccines industry but rather has caused existing companies to re-evaluate their investments in vaccines compared with other segments of their business.
    </p>
    <fig fig-type="figure" position="float" id="fa0">
      <caption>
        <p>EvaluatePharma; World Health Organization; Company financials</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="~/link.aspx?_id=703ED57944CA4764894FF723F5830136&amp;amp;amp;_z=z" />
    </fig>

    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">The barriers to entry for a company with aspirations to be a fully integrated vaccine company involve substantial investment in discovery, development, manufacturing, and commercialization. Although this is true for pharmaceutical firms as well, there are important differences between vaccines and pharmaceuticals including extended product patent life, challenging manufacturing processes, and the need for expertise and relationships in a complex web of global health processes and systems that involve many public and private sector participants.  Taken together, this paints a picture of a unique segment of the biosciences industry that presents opportunity for firms willing to make a sustained commitment of resources and expertise; for these reasons, the vaccines industry is dominated by a few major players, most of which have a long-standing presence.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      In 2014 prior to M&amp;A activity, five companies accounted for over 80% of worldwide vaccines revenue:  <bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/198600186" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>Merck &amp; Co. Inc.</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold>, <bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/198601345" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>Sanofi</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold>/<bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/199200005" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>Sanofi Pasteur</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold>, <bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/198600519" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>Novartis AG</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold>, GlaxoSmithKline, and Pfizer. (<italic>See Exhibit 2</italic>.) The balance of global market revenue is attributable to players with a limited presence in developed markets or a more prominent position in lower-priced middle- and low-income countries.  These revenue figures do not reflect the vibrant activity among many smaller companies that are focusing on developing new vaccines or vaccine technology but with no product revenue or royalty stream at this time.  As expected, the barriers to entry in this latter segment of the vaccine industry are much lower and many of these companies aspire to transactions with major vaccine players rather than vertically integrating their operations.
    </p>
    <fig fig-type="figure" position="float" id="fa1">
      <graphic xlink:href="~/link.aspx?_id=561BC90AA5D2406B90004C42009A9FC1&amp;amp;amp;_z=z" />
    </fig>

    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">The recent spate of activity in the vaccines space has set the stage for a new industry dynamic over the next several years:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet" id="L1">
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">
          April 2014: GlaxoSmithKline buys Novartis&#8217; global vaccines operations. <ext-link xlink:href="" ext-link-type="deal">
            <italic></italic>
          </ext-link>
        </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">
          July 2014: Pfizer acquires Baxter International's two marketed vaccines. <ext-link xlink:href="" ext-link-type="deal">
            <italic></italic>
          </ext-link>
        </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">
          October 2014: CSL buys Novartis' influenza vaccines business. <ext-link xlink:href="" ext-link-type="deal">
            <italic></italic>
          </ext-link>
        </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
        <label>&amp;bull; </label>
        <p content-type="2.2 Story Bullet-List">
          December 2014: Nanotherapeutics buys Baxter BioScience's <italic>Vero</italic> technology and assets. <ext-link xlink:href="" ext-link-type="deal">
            <italic></italic>
          </ext-link>
        </p>
      </list-item>
    </list>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">This M&amp;A activity was driven by a re-assessment of strategic importance of vaccines to the growth objectives of each key player and resulted in a further consolidation among top companies and the resulting exit of two firms from the industry: Novartis and Baxter.  These moves reflect existing strengths, expectations for the growth of the industry over the next several years, and strategic choices related to areas of business focus in a competitive environment.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Sub-head">GSK's Bold Move</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      The most prominent recent move was GlaxoSmithKline&#8217;s announcement in April 2014 that it would acquire Novartis Vaccines, thus merging the portfolios of two of the top five global firms. This acquisition is part of a broader deal between GSK and Novartis valued at a total of $25 billion and involving the sale of oncology assets and creation of a joint venture in consumer products.  GSK has a broad portfolio of vaccines, a global footprint, and total annual vaccine revenue of approximately $5 billion.  Novartis has struggled in the vaccines business with unprofitable results despite a top-line of less than $2 billion.  GSK will pay at least $7.1 billion for the Novartis vaccines portfolio consisting of $5.25 billion in up-front payments, $1.8 billion in milestone payments, and additional annual royalties. (<italic>See Exhibit 3.</italic>)<italic />(Note: This transaction excludes Novartis&#8217; influenza vaccines business, which it sold to <bold>
        <ext-link xlink:href="/c/198600617" ext-link-type="company">
          <italic>CSL Ltd.</italic>
        </ext-link>
      </bold> for $275 million.)  GSK and Novartis announced the completion of this deal in early March 2015 and regulatory authorities in the US, Europe, and elsewhere have approved this transaction including divestiture of GSK's existing meningococcal vaccines portfolio.
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">This move will immediately place GSK as the number one global vaccine firm by revenue, and affirms the company&#8217;s commitment to vaccines as a focus area of investment, while at the same time it marks Novartis&#8217; strategic decision to exit the vaccine industry.  In a press release following the announcement of the transaction, GSK CEO Andrew Witty explained the rationale behind this broader asset exchange with Novartis: &#8220;This deal will transform the shape of the company, significantly bolstering our consumer health care and vaccine operations and be a major step toward fulfilling the company's strategy of creating a simpler, stronger, and more balanced platform for long-term growth.&#8221;  Further commenting on the vaccines portion of this transaction, Witty said, &#8220;The acquisition of Novartis&#8217; vaccines business will significantly enhance the breadth of our vaccines portfolio and pipeline, notably in meningitis.&#8221;</p>
    <fig fig-type="figure" position="float" id="fa2">
      <graphic xlink:href="~/link.aspx?_id=6975BF818D5D4A338100652BC00A034A&amp;amp;amp;_z=z" />
    </fig>

    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      Products to prevent meningitis are indeed at the heart of this deal:  a key opportunity for GSK is the novel meningococcal B vaccine, <italic>Bexsero</italic>.  Meningococcal disease carries a mortality rate of 10% to 15% with significant morbidity among survivors; prior to the recent introduction of Bexsero and <italic>Trumenba</italic> (Pfizer), meningococcal B disease has not been vaccine-preventable. Public awareness of disease caused by the B serogroup increased following outbreaks at Princeton, the University of California, Santa Barbara, and other American universities in 2013, resulting in emergency measures to import and administer Bexsero and turning attention to the fact that a vaccine had not been approved in the US at that time despite approvals elsewhere in the world. Milestone payments from GSK to Novartis are linked to approval and recommendations in the US for Bexsero and eventually, to a combination ABCWY meningitis vaccine.
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">Bexsero was FDA approved in January 2015 through an accelerated review process.  Although meningococcal B disease is indeed devastating, it is also rare, and for that reason and others the Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention&#8217;s (CDC) Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) issued a narrow recommendation for use of meningococcal B vaccines in at-risk populations in February 2015.  This recommendation, for individuals 10 to 25 years of age, includes persons with complement deficiencies, those who are asplenic, those taking specific medications, microbiologists, and those exposed during outbreaks.  These recommendations did not cover college students living in dormitories, military recruits, or travelers.   This &#8220;at-risk&#8221; recommendation effectively limits the use of meningococcal B vaccines to 300,000 to 350,000 individuals &#8211; a small population in comparison to the annual birth cohort of four million in the US.  Responding to the recommendation in an email, Novartis expressed disappointment, saying, &#8220;Today&#8217;s high-risk recommendation does not cover the majority of adolescents and young adults in the United States who are at risk of contracting meningitis B&#8221; but did indicate that the recommendation was &#8220;a step forward.&#8221;</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">Although the ACIP's at-risk recommendation will restrict the commercial opportunity for this product in the short term, the ACIP may consider expanding the recommendation to a broader population in the future, possibly deliberating on this issue as early as June 2015.  ACIP recommendations are crucial to the commercial success of a vaccine in the US since they are often accompanied by public funding through the Vaccines for Children (VFC) Program (as will be the case with Bexsero) and trigger private sector payors (e.g., managed care) to establish guidelines for use and reimbursement of the product.  In addition, a number of public health authorities outside the US use the ACIP guidelines as a reference, thus the deliberations of this committee have a global impact.  In evaluating the expansion of these recommendations in the future, the ACIP will consider the health economics of vaccinating a broader population and will be challenged by the rare incidence of the disease compared with the expense of immunizing a larger population.  In fact, the economics of vaccination against meningococcal B disease resulted in prolonged price negotiations between Novartis and UK authorities following approval of Bexsero and establishment of meningococcal B recommendations in that country. Pricing was set at &#163;20 per dose on March 30, 2015.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Sub-head">GSK Acquires Menveo And Other Assets</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      In acquiring Novartis&#8217; vaccines portfolio, GSK gains immediate access to a small suite of marketed vaccines in addition to Bexsero.  In the US, the largest vaccines market by value in the world, this will allow GSK to participate with Novartis' <italic>Menveo</italic> in the $700 million adolescent segment for quadrivalent meningococcal vaccines (ACWY serogroups).  This puts GSK in head-to-head competition with Sanofi Pasteur, which has dominated the US meningococcal market with <italic>Menactra</italic> since the launch of this product in 2005.  In a two-player market, not uncommon for vaccines, Novartis has achieved an estimated 25% market share with Menveo, which was approved in 2011.  This share level is below what would be predicted by analogy models, and is in part due to Novartis&#8217; narrow product portfolio that has created challenges in constructing an attractive discount program in the privately reimbursed market in the US.  In the private sector, medical practices have a strong incentive to purchase the least expensive product required by the immunization schedule and contract with the fewest vaccine providers for purposes of convenience, thus favoring vaccine manufacturers with a broader portfolio that includes single-source products.   GSK's broader product line in the US will allow for some improved leverage in creating discount programs with the potential to improve the market share of Menveo without the need for increased promotional resources or a change in promotional targeting strategy. However, to increase market share for Menveo in the US, GSK faces the challenge of constructing a discount scheme in the context of a portfolio that lacks single-source products required by the US immunization schedule.
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      Outside the US, GSK has the opportunity to encourage public health authorities to establish recommendations for immunization against ACWY disease and to capitalize on the shift from polysaccharide to conjugate meningococcal vaccines in commercializing Menveo.  In contrast to the US, which has embraced immunization with ACWY conjugate vaccines for adolescent cohorts, public health authorities in other parts of the world, including Europe, have been slower to establish guidelines that require vaccination with meningococcal ACWY conjugate vaccines, often employing immunization programs with meningococcal C vaccines. GSK is familiar with the meningococcal markets outside the US, having licensed its own conjugate and polysaccharide quadrivalent vaccines (<italic>Nimenrix</italic> and <italic>Mencevax</italic>, which will be divested as a result of the acquisition) in a number of countries.  To fully capitalize on the opportunity presented by the acquisition of Menveo, GSK will need to encourage public health authorities to convert or install recommendations for immunization with ACWY vaccines in the face of a disease of relatively low and declining incidence, seemingly effective programs against the C serogroup in a number of countries, and constraints on national health budgets.
    </p>
    <boxed-text>
      <disp-quote>
        <p content-type="2.3 Quote box">
          GSK's challenge is to encourage public health authorities to expand the recommendations for meningococcal B immunization in the US and Europe, create initial preference for Bexsero, and increase market share for Menveo in the US.
        </p>
      </disp-quote>
    </boxed-text>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">The acquisition of Novartis Vaccines represents an opportunity for GSK to increase its vaccine business by making its newly expanded portfolio available to populations in need throughout the world.  Of specific importance, however, is GSK's ability to capitalize on commercial opportunities in the developed markets.  GSK's challenge is to encourage public health authorities to expand the recommendations for meningococcal B immunization in the US and Europe, create initial preference for Bexsero, and increase market share for Menveo in the US.  If GSK is ultimately successful in developing a pentavalent (ABCWY) meningococcal vaccine and recommendations for immunization against meningococcal B disease becomes routine, the convenience of this combination vaccine will provide an important market advantage over administration of the individual components.  Establishment of recommendations for routine immunization with ACWY vaccines in Europe and other markets outside the US represents an additional commercial opportunity.  These challenges will test GSK's ability to execute effectively in the areas of scientific exchange and contracting.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">In addition to the meningococcal assets, GSK acquired a developmental program for group B streptococcus as part of the deal with Novartis.  If successful, this product has the potential to prevent serious perinatal disease in newborns, thus addressing an important public health need that is global in scope and for which no commercialized vaccine currently exists.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Sub-head">Pfizer: Beyond Prevnar To A Broader Portfolio</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      Vaccines represent one of Pfizer&#8217;s six core focus areas for research and development.  Following its unsuccessful attempt to acquire AstraZeneca in 2014, Pfizer has taken an aggressive external approach to bolster its asset position in these focus areas and has strengthened its investment in promising in-house vaccine programs while continuing to invest in pneumococcal vaccine <italic>Prevnar 13</italic> as the cornerstone of its vaccine business.
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      In early 2015, Pfizer announced the acquisition of Redvax, a subsidiary of a <bold>Redbiotec AG</bold>, a Swiss firm. <ext-link xlink:href="" ext-link-type="deal">
        <italic></italic>
      </ext-link> This transaction provides Pfizer access to a preclinical vaccine to prevent cytomegalovirus (CMV), a disease for which there is currently no commercialized preventative vaccine.  CMV infection is prevalent globally across socio-economic strata, and can lead to serious congenital abnormalities such as deafness, learning disabilities, and mental retardation.  Commenting on Pfizer&#8217;s acquisition of Redvax, Kathrin U. Jansen, PhD, Pfizer's senior vice president and chief scientific officer of vaccine research and early development, said, &#8220;We are working to bring innovative vaccines to market that prevent and treat serious diseases.  Through the acquisition of Redvax&#8217;s innovative CMV vaccine platform and expertise, we will seek to develop a vaccine to prevent a difficult disease that can have a devastating and lifelong impact on young children.&#8221;
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      In addition, Pfizer acquired <italic>NeisVac-C</italic> (meningococcal C vaccine) and IMMUN/<italic>TicoVac</italic> (tick-borne encephalitis) from Baxter in late 2014 for $635 million. NeisVac-C is used in a number of countries outside the US where the national vaccination schedules call for routine immunization against meningococcal C disease, allowing Pfizer to participate in markets that have not adopted quadrivalent meningococcal programs.  Total revenue for these products in 2014 was $300 million and immediately provides Pfizer with an incremental cash flow and an expanded commercial portfolio in a number of markets.  These acquisitions, along with the sale of Baxter&#8217;s Vero technology to Nanotherapeutics resulted in Baxter&#8217;s exit from the vaccines industry.
    </p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">Pfizer has several in-house products in various phases of development, including preventative vaccines for Staphylococcus aureus and Clostridium difficile, and therapeutic vaccines for smoking cessation and allergic asthma.  The former two products would represent important breakthroughs in the prevention of deadly diseases for at-risk individuals and provide substantial commercial opportunity in developed markets but are likely several years from market.  These research programs clearly signal Pfizer&#8217;s commitment to a long-term presence in vaccines and its drive to bring innovative products to market.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">While working to expand its vaccine portfolio, Pfizer continues to rely on and invest in Prevnar 13, which will be the foundation for its vaccine revenues over the next several years.  According to a year-end press release by Pfizer, the Prevnar family of products generated $4.5 billion in revenue in 2014 and is Pfizer&#8217;s second-largest product. Importantly, Prevnar 13 is a &#8220;sole-source&#8221; product in the US (i.e., the only pneumococcal conjugate product available), where the immunization schedule calls for vaccination of children against pneumococcal disease with a conjugate vaccine.  The company continues to aggressively invest in Prevnar 13, recently securing US and EU approval in adults aged 65 and older and a label change in the EU to include the results of the CAPITA (Community-Acquired Pneumonia Immunization Trial in Adults); Pfizer is pursuing this label change in the US as well.  To date, Pfizer has been able to avoid significantly discounting this product and has been immune from the commercial weakness that usually accompanies lack of a broader product portfolio due to sole-source status and guidelines that call for immunization of children.  Pfizer&#8217;s progress in expanding its product offerings beyond Prevnar 13 is urgent and important to the long-term success of its vaccines business:  at least one other manufacturer, Merck, is developing a pneumococcal conjugate vaccine that, if approved, will threaten Prevnar 13&#8217;s market dominance.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Sub-head">Trumenba Vs. Bexsero</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">Critical to the successful expansion of Pfizer&#8217;s portfolio is the launch of Trumenba, a vaccine for meningococcal B disease that competes directly with GSK's Bexsero.  Trumenba received FDA approval in October 2014 in an accelerated review process as a three-dose regimen, a disadvantage to the approved two-dose regimen for Bexsero.  Its approval was the Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research&#8217;s first approval of a product holding &#8220;breakthrough therapy&#8221; designation. Although Trumenba was approved several months before Bexsero in the US, both products effectively launch upon establishment of ACIP recommendations, VFC funding, and a CDC contract.  The evolution of meningococcal B recommendations to routine immunization of adolescent cohorts is a very important step for Pfizer, allowing it the opportunity to establish cross-product offerings in the US private sector, potentially using discounts on Prevnar 13 as an incentive.  Susan Silbermann, president of Pfizer Vaccines, expressed the importance of expanded recommendations in a March 2015 press release: &#8220;We believe a recommendation for adolescents and young adults to be vaccinated against serogroup B meningococcal disease can&#8217;t come early enough.  Everyone&#8217;s goal should be to allow enough time for students to start their vaccination before they return to school next fall.&#8221; To expand its meningococcal B franchise beyond the US, Pfizer is currently completing trials for Trumenba in Europe.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">To date, Pfizer&#8217;s approach to expanding its vaccine portfolio has been less dramatic than the large-scale acquisition of Novartis Vaccines by GSK; in large part this reflects the limited availability of, and competition for, late-stage and marketed assets in the vaccine industry.  However, with the approval of Trumenba in the US and investment in development of innovative vaccines such as CMV, S. aureus, and C. difficile, Pfizer has made some promising initial moves designed to strengthen its long-term global presence.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Sub-head">Challenges And Opportunities</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">GSK and Pfizer have made serious commitments to vaccines as part of their overall corporate strategies and are investing heavily in bringing innovative products to market through organic and acquisition efforts.  Beyond the products and programs mentioned here, these companies are also investing in additional licensed vaccines and developmental products and technologies that have the potential to further strengthen their global position over time.  There is also a strong possibility of additional M&amp;A activity, especially by Pfizer, although further individual acquisitions are unlikely to be on the scale of GSK's purchase of Novartis Vaccines.</p>
    <boxed-text>
      <disp-quote>
        <p content-type="2.3 Quote box">
          Success in the market for meningococcal vaccines, especially those that prevent disease caused by the B serogroup, is the first important step for GSK and Pfizer on the road to growth.
        </p>
      </disp-quote>
    </boxed-text>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">Success in the market for meningococcal vaccines, especially those that prevent disease caused by the B serogroup, is the first important step for GSK and Pfizer on the road to growth.  Vaccines to prevent ACWY meningococcal disease have been introduced only within the last decade, and a vaccine to prevent disease caused by the B serotype is an important breakthrough that is just now being introduced.  Although these diseases are global, the priority commercial opportunity is in the relatively well-funded developed markets such as the US and Europe. Success in these markets will provide an important impetus for implementation of guidelines and product adoption elsewhere in the world and support continued efforts by GSK and Pfizer to make these products available globally.  As it relates to prevention of meningococcal B disease, GSK and Pfizer have the common challenge of persuading public health authorities to move beyond narrow risk recommendations in the US and to establish or implement programs in other developed markets through robust, compliant exchange of scientific information, especially health economic analyses.  At the same time, each company needs to position its product as preferred early in the process of market development.   GSK also has an opportunity to capture an increased share of the well-established US market for quadrivalent meningococcal vaccines.  To fully realize these immediate opportunities, each company must overcome execution challenges related to the leverage associated with its product portfolio.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">In addition to the business implications of these recent moves, this effort by GSK and Pfizer has the potential to contribute meaningfully to continued advances in global public health.  With the departure of two of the top five vaccine manufacturers, these companies now carry an even greater burden of providing for the prevention needs of the global community.</p>
    <p content-type="2.2 Story Text">
      <italic>Michael F. Thomas (Michael.Thomas@redteamassociates.com) is a Senior Managing Director at Red Team Associates and was SVP and General Manager at Merck Vaccines and Head of US Vaccines at GSK. William Tam, PhD (William.Tam@redteamassociates.com) is a Senior Consultant at Red Team Associates.</italic>
    </p>
  </body>
</article>